Preliminary Inventory to the Mark Monday Papers, 1961-1984
Hoover Institution Archives
Mark Monday papers
1961-1984
74063
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes, 1 oversize folder, 3 motion picture film reels, 15 phonorecords, 3 phonotape cassettes (2.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, news dispatches, reports, bulletins, pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, and photographs, relating to the Minutemen and other right-wing paramilitary groups in the U.S., and to the Irish republican movement in Northern Ireland. Video use copies of motion picture film available.
Monday, Mark
Access
Collection open for research. Video use copies of motion picture film available.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Biographical/Historical note
American journalist.
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence, writings, news dispatches, reports, bulletins, pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, computer disks, and photographs, relating to the Minutemen and other right-wing paramilitary groups in the United States, the Irish republican movement in Northern Ireland, and Islamic extremist movements. Video use copies of motion picture film available.
Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; Ireland.; Irish unification question.; Journalists.; Minutemen.; Moving-pictures.; Northern Ireland--History--1969-; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.; United States--Politics and government.
- Introduction describing origin of collection, June 6, 1974. (Box 1)
- Reports, 1965-1968.
  - Reports made to Phoenix Police Department, Special Investigations, June - October 1965.
  - Training trip to Colorado, August 26 and 27, 1967.
  - Reports to F.B.I. and interviews, 1967-1968.
- Correspondence, 1966-1968.
- Communications and notes.
  - Use of ammonium nitrate in high explosives.
  - Development of resistance networks.
  - Organization and leadership.
- Training courses.
  - Phase 1, Intelligence, security and propaganda.
  - Phase 2, Intelligence.
  - Phase 3, Security.
  - Phase 4, Propaganda.
  - Phase 5, Recruiting.
  - Training course "B", resistance warfare.
- Bulletins, (publication of the Minutemen)., November 1965-October 1967
- Codes and coded messages.
- "On Target," (monthly publication of the Minutemen, 1966-1967 1966-1967).
- Minutemen publications.
  - "Blueprint for Victory."
  - "Guerrila Warfare."
  - "15 Steps to Victory."
  - "The Minutemen."
  - "Principles of Guerrila Warfare."
  - "We shall fight in the Streets."
  - "The Communist Takeover in America."
  - "Encroaching Government Controls."
- Background news stories on the Minutemen, 1961-1970.
- Articles by Mark Monday on the Minutemen, 1966-1968.
- Unpublished manuscript by Mark Monday on the Minutemen.
- List of supposed Communits, 1967. (Box 2)
- Memorandum to Paul Dean, concerning the Minutemen, 1968.
- File cards used by Minutemen in gathering information on suspected Communists, 1965-1968.
- Map showing sites of Minutemen operations.
- Pamphlet on explosives.
- F.B.I. reports on Minutemen, 1968-1969.
- Notes on Ed Bumgardner, informer for Mark, Monday.
- Material collected by Ed Bumgardner.
  - Patriotic Party.
  - Minutemen.
  - Troy Houghton.
  - Soldiers of the Cross.
- Miscellaneous material.
  - John Franklin letters.
  - Target.
  - We Will Survive.
- Secret Army Organization, 1967-1974.
- Manoeuvers (16 mm motion picture film), undated
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Use copy reference number: 74063_f_0001046
- Unprocessed papers, undated (Box 3-4)
- Declassified British government records, 1978 (Box 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Formerly security-classified record of the British government, released in full. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover
  - Record released in 2010, 1978; One folder containing one document (Box 4)